[Music]
the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet Museum of
hologography
[Music]
hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to another week of holotalk
for the week of April 19th due to a
scheduling Affair where the show's going
up on Monday night instead of Sunday
night Our Guest this week is Steve
McGrew from New Light Industries limited
and Steve will be with us in just a
moment but before we go to Steve I just
want to mention something to the
listeners and you know I've always
wanted to do something special for the
Holo talk listeners I think I have
something that I can do that will be
considered a little bit special and
here's what it's going to be this week I
have the 35 milliwatt diode coming in
and this is going to be a very very
important test for holography because
we're going to find out if this 35
milliwatt diode is going to produce a
hologram we've had a lot of luck with
the smaller diodes that are contained in
the laser pointers and also with the 15
milliwatt diode from a few weeks back
but you talk about 35 milliliter going
up into 50 milliliters so you're getting
into some very significant power to
create some very nice large format
display hologram so this is an important
test so what I'm going to do for the
whole talk listeners is this
next week I am not going to send out any
announcement of the show
and what I'm going to do is when you log
on whoever does log on is definitely
going to be a true holotalk listener
because they're not going to need the
reminder to tune in that I send out with
the email each week and what I will do
is when that show starts up we will
cover the 35 milliwatt diode tests in
that show but also I will give you a URL
or a web page to go to to see and read
about the results I'll have photos up
there of the actual laser diode module
I'll take photos of the Holograms that
are created if it does in fact create
Holograms and you will be the first
people to be able to see the results of
this test by tuning in to the whole talk
show
and then later on in the week I will
add change that address because if
you've been following the experiments
done with the laser diode you know that
the first diode page is like diode and
then there's diode one diode two all the
way up I think we're up to diode 13.
well this is not going to be diode 14.
this will be a special web address that
you won't be able to get if you listen
to the whole talk show
and then later on on the week I'll take
that page and put it into the normal
sequence of pages which will make it the
diode 14
HTML on the site itself so if you're a
whole talk listener next week you will
not receive an email update for the show
like you receive each week if you're on
the email list and don't forget to tune
in even though you don't receive that
reminder because it'll be a special show
for you we'll cover the results of the
35 milliwatt diode and I will also give
you the web page address that you can
type into your browser and go and see
the results before anyone else gets a
chance to see them and hopefully that's
something that will be special for a lot
of the whole talk listeners out there
let's move on right away to the
interview with Steve McGrew it was a
very nice interview I enjoyed it very
much it was early in the morning had a
chance to sit down with a cup of tea and
talk to Steve about his many many years
involved in the field of Photography and
the different projects that he worked on
in the past and also the new project his
company is currently working on at
present and you also find a link to the
new light Industries limited website
right on the whole talk page and before
we go to Steve here's a message from my
studio and as soon as that message is
over we'll go right into the interview
I'm not going to come back on after the
interview's over so I will say thank you
now for tuning in and I hope you tune in
each and every week to whole talk the
internet's laser and holography talk
show this is Frank de Freitas take care
would you like to make your own
one-of-a-kind hologram and learn how you
can start making holograms on your own
at the same time you do this and much
more by attending one of Frankie's
greatest holography workshops from
beginner to Advanced Frank's got a
workshop that's just right for you from
single afternoon evening or weekend
introductory workshops to Wednesday
evening five-week complete courses and
don't forget his newest Workshop laser
pointer holography located just off the
Northeast Extension of the Pennsylvania
Turnpike and Interstate 78 video is a
quick non-stop drive from the New York
Philadelphia and Baltimore Washington DC
areas for more information call the
Studio's toll-free hotline at
1-800-458-3525 and begin your own
Journey with holography today that's
1-800-458-3525 for more information on
attending Frankie Freitas holography
Workshop today
foreign
you tell the listeners a little bit
about your background in holography how
you got started and where you got to
where you are now okay so you want you
want you want my whole history huh yeah
here and there did you really work down
at holex in Norristown yeah I'm just
north of Norristown in Allentown PA
here's what I knew about holex said
started by two guys named Goldberg yes
is that true okay not Brothers nope not
Brothers okay yeah and they were
neighbors yes they in fact they lived at
different ends of a single duplex no
kidding one was a physicist and another
one was a
um I think he was a marketing guy yeah
or CPA
with UTA I'm not sure
and um Scott and emsel nem Val was hired
about the same time I was shortly before
yeah what
um
what type of holograms did you do I
think I have a couple of the early holex
Holograms but I'm not absolutely certain
did you do transmission Holograms there
a Rolex
before I arrived there had a
sort of a mass production system
for silver halide film Holograms
they had some Air Force
film transports that were used in aerial
reconnaissance or something
from Roll to roll developing
stuff and made Holograms that I think
were primarily sold through admin
scientific and places like that that's
where I got mine I bet you I have them a
couple of the early holex Holograms and
they were all the laser viewable type
they also if I remember correctly they
had also a
a viewer that I think used a sodium lamp
and a filter and it worked really well
yeah
then I've been working in in Europe at
europlex and uh came back here and went
to work then for the whole X and I was
hired based basically to set up a mass
production system for BCG Holograms okay
so that's what I did
and in the process worked out the
techniques for
controlling the color on dcg hologram
which is tough to do in Philadelphia
area I bet it wasn't that bad
um
funny help when you get a
process set up but as long as you keep
all the parameters under control it
always works the same way yeah did you
have to environmentally control things
not really no no kidding I had to do
things not leave stuff
out yeah and as long as you know it
turned out not to be a problem
while I was there uh Jerry and I worked
together for
prove what he was doing and I set up
some modifications there
'd make rainbow Holograms
so they were doing some mass production
of those
then Mike long came to work as my
assistant
and
after I left
holex he ended up being their chief
philographer
you uh start up late Impressions after
you left tolex
um here's some colex and then I went to
work for
holophonics okay slash holotron in
Richland Washington uh that company
self-destructed very quickly and left me
marooned down in Sunnyvale California
and that's where I started light
impressions
here's a story I've heard okay and tell
me if this is true or not because this
could be an urban legend it said that
you came up with the idea for uh doing a
lot of the embossed Holograms while
sitting at a desk and playing with silly
putty on a comic book
that's a wonderful urban legend is that
true we shouldn't mess it up but it's
not true no kidding no kidding have you
heard that before no never have yes they
tell everybody you can you can think of
it's a great Legend yeah it's just a
flash that came on to you when you were
taking Silly Putty and putting it down
onto a comic book and you appeal the
Silly Putty back and you know how you
would get the image on the Silly Putty
from the ink and that's when you had a
flash of uh embossed telegraphy that's a
good story but it's not true no kidding
well you heard it here first
I'll tell you the first mention I ever
hologram embossing
things
I was in San Francisco visiting uh
Multiplex
and Steve Benton was there and he was
talking about how someone ought to
hologram embossing
bossing and he mentioned that that there
were a bunch of companies that were
embossing diffraction grades and he
mentioned the diffraction company
and said that there were some others
So eventually I attract I tracked down
the diffraction company I found that
nobody was embossing Holograms and then
I did a literature search and found that
that RCA had done a fair amount of work
recording holograms on photoresist and
they actually embossed Holograms but
they weren't
Holograms that would be useful to
holographers they went for a videotape
and the efficiency they got was down
around three percenters wasn't really
good and the methods they use weren't
really good but the the basic principles
of recording the Holograms on
photoresist were perfectly good they
just needed some assignment
so that's what I did I always thought
that the whole grams that came out of
light Impressions were beautiful well
thank you at the time I completely
thought that they were the best in whole
and best whole grams on the market
effects then it was so Crystal Clear I
mean the the color not not just the
crispness of the work that was done but
the actual colors themselves were just
it was almost like looking at a grating
a very high quality grading
well a fair amount of thought went into
picking the spatial frequencies to get
those colors
um there are there are
diagrams chromaticity diagrams and so on
that can be really helpful in picking
the right wavelengths so that's that's
what I did but I I would say that
Christmas
and the brightness of the Holograms came
from two things one was the particular
2D 3D technique that we used
um gives you sharp edges and it's still
the
bit using those contact masks
uh the other is we had a
a company culture of of don't send it
out unless it's as good as good as it
get it yeah and we threw away a lot of
hologram Masters because of that but I
think it paid off you know a lot a lot
of people collect those type of
holograms now and I wouldn't be
surprised in the future if they weren't
considered Collectibles well I hope so
for instance I have the that's one of
your famous uh pieces of work is the
Reese's Pieces
stickers oh boy yeah
what's special about mine is I have a
complete uncut sheet of all the stickers
together
well that's neat and I don't think there
are too many of those out there no there
aren't they're very
yes I don't think I have one so that
that would be considered collectible
well that was actually the first of the
2D 3D yeah before that there were some
straight 2DS but that was the first two
background no kidding that's a good
collectible yeah
so uh I hold that close to my heart
that's great now this company you have
now new light Industries limited yeah
you've got a few interesting projects
that you're working on out there the
holographic image Setter which I'd like
to point out to people probably doesn't
have a lot in common with the photo type
setting or the regular image Setters
that we normally see in graphic arts and
uh
pre-press Industries
but once you tell us knew about that
well it's what I'd call an advanced dot
matrix hologram printer
the what makes it Advanced is
some of the features it it's
basic dot resolution is about two
thousand knots per inch but inside each
dot we can store an image
that image
in essence has resolution down to about
twenty thousand knots
well
uh the
grading frequency
is continuously variable
over whatever range we choose which
means you can pick any special frequency
you want and assign that frequency to a
DOT a DOT on the Fly what are the main
problems that we're looking at in
creating an image Setter that will be
able to actually point out the
interference pattern to reconstruct a
three-dimensional object
that's that's quite a ways down the road
I would imagine isn't it no it really
isn't
um and it can be done right now I think
there's several trade-offs if you want
to use a standard
.matrix printer you need to be able to
put a lot of dots into one little
resolution element let's say a
resolution element is about
five thousandths of an inch on a side
because anything bigger than that you
can see with your naked eye
so as long as you can put a lot of
a lot of dots inside that
spatial frequencies you can build what
amounts to a pixel that
that contains well let's see if you had
a thousand DPI
and uh your resolution elements like
that you'd have 25
different spatial frequencies you could
put into that one dot if you have higher
resolution that goes up to
uh then
then it's four times that so you get to
the point where you can put as much
information into one resolution element
as you can into uh
comparable size on a rainbow
at that point you can build a 3D image I
don't think that's the easiest way to do
it yeah the assist we have called
them and there's a path that people can
look that up on our web page uh that
makes those dots directly without all
the computation you have to go through
to do
and it's still a DOT by dot recording
process but each dot
is created
specifically so that it has a set of
spatial frequencies
orientations and things that a
comparable dot in a rainbow hologram
would have
would have it and how long would you say
it takes to actually print one of those
Holograms out give you know given a size
of you know a couple inches by a couple
inches it's a young process well the
system doesn't exist currently okay
we're building it but and it should be
done around the end of this year but our
Target is to record these dots at five
thousand per inch and we think that
we'll be able to reach about 40 excuse
me five thousand per second and we think
we'll be able to reach around forty
thousand in a second
now you don't do this work as much as
you do design and build these systems
correct uh yeah our our business is not
making hologram Masters we just yeah now
someone had one of these holographic
image Setters and they wanted to set
something up as a service for send them
they can accept different file formats
and bring those file formats in is there
a software program that the uh the
graphic needs to go through before it's
sent to the image Center uh we we
provide the software that and we wrote
the software that that will convert from
a BMP to our format so basically you can
do the artwork design in any any art
program yeah
it's uh basically for line art or you
could also take a photo and somehow
manipulate the photo a little bit and
have some sort of result from that as
well or a graphic logo you can
manipulate a photo of
um we don't yet have all the features
we'd like to to to work with photos but
so basically yeah it's graphics and line
art and things of that nature it's like
logos clip it logos yeah sure
now you also have the Hologram reader
which will read a hologram and measure
its authenticity that system
was originally developed last year uh
funding from bmdo the ballistic missile
defense organization their interest I
believe was because the image processing
and image recognition techniques that
we've developed
could be useful for for identifying
incoming missiles and separating them
from decoys
really fast and manages a lot of data I
think the reader is going to make quite
a difference
in making Holograms more secure you have
a ton of patents at your website and I
would suggest anybody that is interested
in what it is you're doing and also able
to research some of the other patents
that are involved with photography to
head over there how many patents do you
have you've got a ton on that web page
I don't know how many are on the web
page I think I think I've got 25
currently issued and a handful pending
wow
and you know
it's a lot of sleepless nights I imagine
you mean writing patents sir why even a
man making sure that no one's going
against them and things like that well
yeah writing them is the fun part to get
into patent litigation and you do lose a
lot of sleep yeah it's very it's not a
fun thing let's jump back to 1982. okay
for some of the listeners that are on
here that maybe even beginning the
photography this this would be an inch
of interest to them because you had a
paper which you presented at the
Symposium the International Symposium at
lakefosh for a graphical method of
controlling color and Holograms yeah
I've always called this the hinge Point
geometry that's what I call it is that
what you call it because you know I was
just looking at the article earlier
today and there's nowhere in the article
where I picked up the term hinge Point
geometry and I'm trying to think well
where did I ever hear that this was
called hinge Point geometry
but that's right sure yeah why don't you
tell the uh listeners a little bit about
that paper because that's one of the
areas that a lot of people like to move
on to is doing multiple color Holograms
and it's a very easy method right
yeah it is an easy method way back when
I was I was developing the 2D 3D
technique color control was
a top priority
and there are these equations that that
you can manipulate to tell you what
angled wavelengths and so on to use but
this sort of cumbersome and some people
who don't have a strong math background
they're not very useful
so I set out to to develop a mechanical
or a graphical visual method for
producing the same results that the
equations would and it turns out that
you can build a little mechanical
linkage
that solves the equations
so I went from that from designing a
mechanical linkage to working out a
technique for just working out the the
angles on graph paper with a cup is
finished hmm
and it ended up so simple and so kind of
obvious that I wrote up a paper on it
and actually John Kaufman presented that
paper yes your wife is expecting that's
right that's right he wasn't actually
born during the conference but he could
have been yeah
but I love to be there for it how does
he know uh 16. yeah I could have done
that math but I'm just fine
16. do you have any other children yeah
I have a seven-year-old just turned
eight hey no kidding and I've got a
daughter who's in her early 30s wow and
had a bunch of grandkids no kidding we
there's a lot of families out there in
holography that we don't hear much about
we hear about the people that work in
holography but we never picture them
have in the family well it's funny you
know we were all pretty young when we
started in this and now
funny things a few decades have gone by
yeah we should all get together for a
clambake someday you know Posey Jackson
used to do that remember that but yeah
Long Island yeah the Hamptons
that's right yeah yeah that was fun so
I'd like to put a link also to that
specific page for your graphical method
because a lot of people are starting to
do Holograms with these inexpensive
laser diodes now oh great yeah and I
have a 35 minute of that coming in this
week
35 milliwatts of panel okay 650
nanometers which works out okay with
some of the materials that I'm using
because they have a spike at 647 for
Krypton and the whole thing if you were
to buy the set of parts of the diode the
collimating lens the barrel and the
driver she runs around two hundred
dollars
correct 35 milliamps of power that's
awesome that's incredible when you
compare that to a 35 milliwatt
spectrophysics he need okay so it's
allowing people to get involved with
photography that normally you would not
want to put out a lot of money to get
involved with it and I think doing
multiple car holography is probably one
of the most rewarding creative things
that you can do in holography in your
paper is just absolutely perfect for
that because I used your paper when I
started to do polar holography back in
the 80s well you
know in that paper I think that the part
that was a real Innovation other people
had been
in color transmission Holograms but
the Innovative part of that paper is
almost
almost and that's the color control
techniques for reflection holes yes yes
uh John Kaufman had a need for that and
control I was doing in
and asked how to apply that to
reflection Holograms I worked that out
he tried it and it worked really well I
love multiple color reflection biography
it's beautiful like Hoffman I guess has
to be considered the best I remember the
test he did he that really proved it was
working it was a it was a the end of a
tree branch that had Twigs going in all
directions the whole image was about a
foot deep
and he was trying to get all the
different color components to
superimpose through that whole volume
it's really hard but but it turns out
that if the geometry is followed just
just right and the color the swelling
and all that sort of thing has done
appropriately
they match up perfectly
really rewarding
well Steve is there anything you want to
add before we close this up to any
topics that you'd like to bring up an
announcement on a project or something
no I can't think of anything I welcome
people to come see our webpage and
will be updating it as new developments
come along okay and we will have a link
in fact there is a link to the new Light
Industry limited website on the whole
talk page if you scroll down you'll see
the link right there as it is every week
for our guests where you can go and
visit their website and see what it is
that they're doing Steve after all these
years I finally had a chance to talk to
you it's a pleasure to talk with you and
believe it or not people from all over
the world because logging on to hear
this show I keep track on who comes
through and I don't know them personally
I just get IP numbers and I can
transpose those IP numbers into areas of
the uh country or the the IP originated
from there's about 42 countries that log
on to listen to this
on a good Monday excuse me you know I
usually I put the show up Sunday night
tonight it'll go up on Monday night on a
good first day there's usually at least
a thousand listeners the first day uh
the the most I've ever had was um I
think it was a thousand thirteen and a
thousand thirty three that was um
year and the one for this year's show
has actually been eighteen hundred
that's very impressive isn't that
something that is no other place to get
it and it's a it's immediate information
and telegraphy I mean it's safe to have
to get information in holography anyway
I mean this is immediate terrific you
know you're doing a great job well thank
you very much Steve I appreciate that
and thank you for taking the time to be
a guest on the show nice talking to you
take care Steve bye
foreign